ch
[Music]
[Applause]
I
am I and
is
[Music]
juru
[Applause]
[Music]
the
[Applause]
[Music]
good
C
[Music]
Shanty Shanty
shanty mahaj
[Music]
om
before we introduce tonight's program we
would like to welcome one of our
presenters who arriv to the Asom today
and this is Amy wi welcome
Amy Amy is the author of the bestselling
yoga for depression and she's an expert
in the the field of uh training yoga
teachers to work with um people with
depression and anxiety in other um moods
and she's um going to start her training
she comes here every year to teach this
course it's going to start on Thursday
it's called yoga for depression
practitioner training course and
tomorrow afternoon she will give an
introduction at 2 p.m. it's an open
Workshop it's called meeting the tamasic
mood so uh this is at 2 uh tomorrow in
on Garden West platform open to everyone
and still possible to join the course
the course begins on Thursday and it's a
six day course seven days
course so welcome and tonight we
continue with the program with KES Mel
roach on what is Nirvana and how do we
get there and like yesterday we will
start with some music and so we welcome
gu M Ro and Mercedes let us welcome
no can you hear Sor yeah uh so we're
going to play the song it's a very uh
ancient song from
Israel uh it's a song of morning
uh but the sense of it is a song of
morning just before a great a great
gladness okay
St
[Music]
see
J
[Music]
little
tiny
Child by
[Music]
my
little oh sister
to how may we
do for
two of this
[Music]
day
this
for we
sing my
[Music]
then child for
the and never
[Music]
more for
party
Sing
Sing by
[Music]
by the
little
tiny
Child by the
[Music]
the the
little
[Music]
tin my by
[Applause]
you
[Music]
all so uh this is the second night on
no
uh last night weal oh there's a reading
uh
I'm taking selections from uh many many
scriptures and sort of translating them
and putting them into the readings but
uh guish Michael always does it at the
last minute so we didn't quite get them
all printed uh for tonight but you'll
get it tomorrow you'll get each day a
little bit late so cuz we're doing it as
we have free time uh but there are
hundreds of pages about nirvana in the
Tibetan scriptures and they're very
beautiful so it's kind of a hard it's a
difficult thing to choose which things
to to
share so last night we talked about
nurana as having three different
meanings the word having three different
meanings uh Nur means not or down or out
or and Van we talked about V three
meanings of Van last night one was uh
near in the sense of blowing out a
candle uh or extinguishing all of our uh
negative thoughts did you guys meditate
about what's your worst negative thought
mean one person told me but they got
angry while they were telling
me no just kidding but I almost got
jealous and
then anybody want to share a few or too
shy I I told mine you should tell yours
main main
pleasure
anger okay that's not very
original
any desire for what Pringles be myself
up say again oh beating myself up yeah
good yeah beating yourself up that's
great two more then I'll start I'm
holding
upti say again impatient
I in what sense fear of death yeah
impatience impatience impatience okay
one more one more expectation
of expectation of
pleasure okay is the word expectation is
that a uh he asked his expectation and
negative emotion what do you think I
think it could be and it could not be
right I think expectation of becoming
Nirvana is okay and then expectation
that you're going to get a promotion
that you don't
deserve that can turn into a
expectations of other
people oh in the sense that let other
people might let you down I think that
can be a place I think
so uh it depends on how you perceive the
other person if you perceive that
they're coming from
you and they let you down then you
wouldn't get upset then it's not a clure
you see uh but if you thought they were
letting you down from their own side not
due to anything you've ever
done then no then they upset feeling
would tend to be Amplified because it's
based
on ignorance okay so then that would
come as
a did anybody have any questions from
yesterday about about
anything okay and I don't feel bad I
didn't give any time you're about to be
a a temporary experience very beautiful
question uh he said Can Nirvana be a
temporary experience and there's a
debate about it and I'm going to cover
it
hopefully uh some people say you can
drop down out of Nana uh okay some
people say second
question yesterday you never used the
word equinity the entire time you were
talking it sounded like you were talking
about a state of perfect
Equity definition of n okay then he
asked about
economic so about dropping down out of
Nana
uh there's two two schools of Sal and
some lower schools of Buddhism say it is
possible to drop down on of Nirvana and
then the higher schools say that yeah
you have to say that because the reason
you guys think you can get to Nirvana is
mistaken and uh I'll go into it briefly
I mean the lower schools
believe that Nirvana is uh achieved
through something
called which means
uh in the yog
it's Thea
and uh
I think I don't know anyway in tibetan
it means
uh if you reach a place where you have
overcome your anger simply because
you're getting more and more deep into
your meditation progressively more
deep uh without content okay so you're
just becoming more peaceful because you
are breathing
low or uh you're trying not to think
about anything or like that you're just
trying to calm the mind the process of
progressively calming your mind until it
becomes deeper and deeper into a
Stillness is not enough to stop your
anger forever and you will drop back out
okay so that's considered a a uh a trap
to think that uh just uh finding finally
uh a house where the neighbors are
quiet and uh no I mean these are all
temporary things right I found a house
where the neighbors are quiet I got my
children to leave you know I uh no and I
uh you know and I stopped coffee and
then I stopped tea and then I stopped
green tea and then I stopped DEA and I'm
down to water no there's a feeling that
you're making progress and your mind is
more and more
calm uh but those are dependent on outer
circumstances that's not you haven't uh
addressed the root of anger uh so
so a stopping of anger which which comes
about through only deep
meditation we in yoga terms inanga terms
I think you could
say andana without samadi you see so uh
not talking about the content but simply
the focus and the duration of the focus
uh and Jana it would feel like you're
overcoming your anger but then the first
time the kids come
back uh you get angry again you see you
haven't addressed the root of the
problem which is aidia using the
meditation to stop aidia and then that
stops anger permanently and you cannot
drop out at that okay so it's a good
question second question was equinity
UPA
uh UPA is used in the teachings on
nirvana in a in a beautiful teaching uh
called the difference between personal
Nirvana and enlightened Nirvana and
we'll talk about that so there are two
different kinds of uh Nirvana and it in
according to Buddhist the highest
schools of Buddhism it is possible to
reach Nirvana which is Everlasting
permanent
um and not have compassion it's possible
okay there are people who can do that so
just by raw understanding of Ultimate
Reality and without a burning concern
for other people it's possible to stop
your anger forever it is possible and
then you become sort of a selfish little
grub
Nirvana okay there's a word for it like
that it's called s s means uh they call
it rhino rhinoceros like Nirvana and and
then you ask the Lama what what do you
mean it's an old Sanskrit term and uh
you said what's a roseros like Nana and
they say rosanes don't like to hang out
with other
rosanes they just want to be by
themselves so it's that that kind of
Nirvana is the technical term is CA
which means rhinocerous like
so it is
possible technically uh to reach what
happens then is you you go into some
kind of a spaced out personal happiness
Nirvana and then there's a beautiful uh
description in scripture about how the
Buddhas of the 10 directions are
watching you space out in your little
personal rhinoceros n and they come and
they tap you on the shoulder
you know like they actually enter your
mind um you know and they they almost
like mentally tap you on the shoulder
and say Hey you know we got to move on
from here uh because otherwise you would
stay there
forever uh and one of the things they
teach you then is uh the four
immeasurables
M they teach you those for um we call
them causes for compassion they teach
you four attitudes that you can find in
the yoga
Sutra uh which is based MIT tree meaning
the desire that others be happy karuna
the desire that they not have pain uh
murita the desire that they find a
higher happiness of Liberation and then
UPA meaning equinity in the sense that
the first three are directed towards all
all people without
prejudice which is very beautiful so
number four is the first three D Ed all
living creatures without prejudice uh so
in that sense UPA would come up the
equinity would come up that eventually
you would want to share that Nirvana
with all living beings equally and
that's the meaning of equinity in N yeah
it's a very beautiful question I hope to
get that the tapping process is a very
interesting thing uh so we'll talk about
this okay uh let's move on
so we talked about uh nirvan in the
sense of blowing out and I didn't say
but you already know that the word
English words fan and ventilation then
uh come from Van right a a in Sanskrit
often changes to an e in English and a v
is interchangeable with an F or a p so
you get fan or you get ventilation
meaning to blow blow out niron then we
talked about niron as unweaving
something
vaa uh the unweaving of of the illusion
which is what enables you to blow out
the candle so the two vas are related
you unle the illusion which is near vah
and then you reach
nirvana blowing out of your negative
emotions and that is to destroy the
enemy which is
niran okay so van means to Vanquish it
came into the word Vanquish and those
are the three vs we have l
so this is an interesting thing I mean
for me I think for Swami G for people
who spend their lives with this sort of
thing which I feel happy to be here
because I don't get to meet many people
like s g um who really enjoy these
things but
um the Chinese uh struggled the Tibetans
and the Chinese both struggled with how
to translate the word
Nirvana and uh there the uh we'll talk
about it later but the the Schwan song
who is the Chinese translator of many of
the early Buddhist scriptures uh he said
there are five uh
different uh reasons not to translate a
foreign word into your current language
you know whether you're speaking Hebrew
or English or
Spanish uh this uh shanong said um you
know there are five kinds of words that
you should not translate and because the
Chinese uh decided to translate Nirvana
as
Nan they didn't translate it they just
made the sounds the two characters just
mean me and fun and they just they're
just the sounds of n it would be as if
in English we chose to keep the words
Nirvana rather than say did you would
you blowing out yet you see I mean and
in English we have made that decision I
think already we have chosen in English
I don't know about what the situation in
Buenos is but um you but in in English
we have chosen to not translate and to
you and then uh he he gives um he gives
some guidelines on when not to translate
a word and I think they might be
interesting you see uh he said when the
word is used in a mantra and it's secret
uh then you shouldn't translate it um me
see I what the rest
then he said um if the word has so many
different connotations in Sanskrit that
it would be a shame to restrict it to a
single meaning by using a translation
and he gives the example of
bavan uh which in traditional Buddhist
literature is said to have 16 different
meanings so it would be a shame to pick
one of them and and translate it so he
said leave it alone and Nirvana is like
that I think Nirvana has so many sweet
meanings that it would be ashamed to
call it blowing out and miss the
unweaving you see then he said uh if
everyone got used to the foreign word
and it would upset people like s Sam
Sara is a mispronunciation it's wrong
it's like
Moscow uh which is Mos right and it
should be SAR is the correct Sanskrit
but people are so used to it that it
would be confuse everybody if I use Sara
all night right so then he said in that
case you should just leave it uh the way
the way people are mispronouncing it if
if it has become General usage then
leave it alone because you just confuse
people and then the other one was was
where a use of a foreign word would lend
the idea of sense of mystery which is
desirable uh you know like when you say
Nirvana it has a certain sexy mystery to
it you know and then to to nail it down
as blowing it out it would not be so
sexy so you know it's a beautiful idea
that they had so in Chinese they just
call it NE but then they Define it as me
which means uh the ending of suffering
the sociation of suffering so I think
we'll get into that later but the
Tibetans they chose to translate it and
and they had two choices they could have
done what they call a a meaning
translation they could have done a word
translation so were they going to just
call it blowing out or should they call
it Liberation you see the
difference uh and they chose to
um they chose to use a literal
translation so they call
it try to
[Music]
say then the word Nirvana is so used
inat constantly every moment uh it got
shortened like we don't say Do not in
English anymore we say don't and in
tibetan they don't
say they say
say yeah so it got
smushed uh into a single sound because
everyone's talking about Nirvana all the
time and they don't have time to
say they
okay so but it's a beautiful word and it
and I thought to start tonight with that
okay means grief okay like that kind of
fit the song I kind of thought the song
would be nice it's a song of grief and
you can feel it even if you don't know
the song you feel in the in the in this
melody it's a song of sadness and grief
and then L DEA means to go beyond grief
to to transcend
uh grief so the Tibetans chose to
translate each part of the word Nirvana
as going Beyond grief okay
um then I thought to give you over the
centuries how people have defined the
grief in Yana okay so here we go I'm
going to read
some uh there's a llama very close llama
in our lineage uh called
Quicksilver uh who lived in the 1800
18th century and he said grief is how a
mother feels when she has only one child
and she loves that child you know I just
had a
friend uh she's a teacher at our
University who had a baby and Ora you
know Ora she came here long ago uh so
she just had a baby and
and uh I saw her me and jig May saw her
the other day and you try to talk to her
but it's hopeless uh she's got this
little chubby thing on her lap it's like
Oney old now and she talks she says
three words and then she kisses the
child on the head and then she looks
back up at you and she forgot what you
were talking about it's really
frustrating you know I finally just took
the baby away from her and we had a
conversation uh but you you try to think
of a a woman like that who that's her
only child uh and how she can't stop
from kissing the child every few minute
every less than a minute the child gets
a kiss you know I don't know what she's
going to L her uh but uh if the child
died suddenly you know which happens
right I mean children don't wake up or
something it happens and then how how
the mother feels is you see that's the
first meaning of the grief that you go
beyond When You Reach Nana okay that's
the first meaning second one uh this is
a commentary called uh the joys of
confession proper confession to your to
your own uh Guru for example I mean that
used to be my favorite unfavorite thing
to do was to go to my I had to go tell
my Guru the bad things I had done and it
was in incredible embarrassing and what
do you call it shameful and it's very
healthy uh it's very good so this is a
book called the praise of confessing in
front of your Guru okay I'm not
suggesting that you do it
uh and and he says
uh real
grief uh we we talked yesterday about
the most stupid thing you could do when
somebody called you stupid right what
was
it yeah you call back okay cuz that
creates a mini
sansara okay that's a good example of
the meaning of the word sansara so
sansara doesn't have to be this Global
thing of suffering many Saras are being
thrown into motion all the time so
meaning a downward cycle or a
self-perpetuating cycle of pain you
someone calls you stupid
because you called someone stupid last
week and then you get angry and you say
no you're stupid and then you plant an
you stupidly plant another uh person
next week to come back and call you
stupid right so that's a sansara that's
the meaning of sansara you started a
cycle a self uh perpetuating cycle in
motion so uh in the in that commentary
it said you want to know what grief
is grief is having to watch the people
of the world throw little Suns SARS into
MO emotion constantly you see grief is
having to watch people respond to other
people with violence constantly and know
they will suffer in a week the same
injury you see that's grief he said if
you want to know what grief is you see
in this theory that Swami G has been
teaching us Lord
Krishna and and and what we've been
saying for years the whole theory is
that everything bad that happens to is
is coming because you hurt somebody else
right so
then the implication of that is that
every suffering in the world was
avoidable every single uh War every
single famine uh every single unkind
word said by one person to another in
the history of this planet was
unnecessary it was just a boooo you see
it was a a viya you know we just didn't
know what to do and every single small
pain of someone calling you stupid up
to a nuclear blast over Hiroshima or
something these were all C caused
unnecessarily they could have been
avoided if people had known what to do
you see and then grief yen is to watch
the world continue to suffer unnecessary
if it was necessary if it was
unavoidable it wouldn't be so bad but if
it was all a mistake if it was just all
wrong
thinking uh that's a s thing that's a
tragedy that's a tragedy of of of human
history okay that's that's maybe tragedy
would be a good one for young see get
that feeling okay third
one this is master vasu who wrote the
aiakos which is one of our most famous
uh it's one of the five Great books that
we
study grief is part of the painful
process of getting old and then dying
and we feel it when we are torn from
those we love or even when we must
encounter Those whom we
dislike okay so he's from the fourth
Century he's defining grief in
Nirvana as
uh the innate condition of humankind
that all people must be old and all must
all Must Die unless they overcome a viya
you know okay they must
die if a person is not in this asham or
a similar place of study they must get
old and die there's no choice okay they
must get all and die you know and I
speak a lot at yoga studios you know I'm
calling on a lot to speak at yoga
studios and then I can't help but uh
feel bad you know I'll be in a I went to
a very famous un of New York the teacher
is is very beautiful D he's a very
very kind and and very very
extraordinary Yogi who does Nana what
you call Shas right headstand with no
arms his balance is so good he does a
head down you know on a there's a photo
of him
in bog or
something yeah on top of a sewer what
you
call man manhole C in downtown New York
like this upside down and uh but he got
old you know he just done an operation
and and he's the person that you would
think is the healthiest Yogi in the
world he doesn't eat anything bad and
and uh he got old and
uh that's all he got old while he was
doing
yoga yeah 2 hours in yoga you're 2 hours
closer to your
duck you
are and your bones are two hours more
brittle and that's how they break
finally enough of those young classes
and then
finally no it's always like that so
anyway he says that's grief if you want
to know what grief is it's the condition
that unless we are able to undertake
extraordinary spiritual practices which
you are learning in this
life the higher meanings of of the deep
yoga practices then you must die and you
must get off
okay uh another ancient Indian Buddhist
he said passing Beyond grief simply
means to stop all your suffering and
we'll talk more about
that kitra who's another Buddhist
scholar and he said passing Beyond grief
is to destroy all the impurities within
you Vita
DEA I like his uh he said passing Beyond
grief is reaching happiness and gaining
the ability to stay there without ever
losing it okay I think and and in the
reading the first page has a quotation
from Lord
Buddha uh it's he said he he was asked
he was called upon to Define nirvana in
a Sutra called the Sutra of the great
Nirvana which is the book which explains
Nirvana more than anything and in there
he starts out he just says Nirvana means
happy
okay if you want to know what Nirvana is
it's just to be happy and and he doesn't
say you know that's all he says the DEA
adds and to be able to stay there right
okay um then chony Lama who's probably
the best of all of these Masters because
he comes from a monastery called
sarame which is my monory uh he in the
1600s uh he wrote uh a beautiful
commentary on The Diamond Cutter sura
which is the
only it's the only uh commentary in
existence uh in tiet on the diamond C
and he said uh the grief that we
transcend when we speak up going Beyond
grief in Nirvana is first of all the
grief of our past Karma and
claas and is and it is the grief of all
of our pain so he says Nirvana means
he's going Beyond suffering but he's
more precise and and all of the great
schools of Buddhism follow that
uh it's not just to go beyond suffering
it's to transcend the causes of
suffering which are which is our
misunderstanding things okay so Nirvana
for him means to stop your suffering
because you finally understand where
it's coming from all right so that's
that's his version of going Beyond
grief then I put in two selections from
the Buddha
himself uh cuz I like them and it's too
long to read all right uh but
I'll one is one is uh I'll read one uh
quickly the other one's too long to read
I think and and you have it all right
but I'll read the one it says we create
the six objects of the senses like ice
cream from the boutique and we throw
ourselves into the pain of the six
different kinds of craving the terror
that this brings us is the grief which
we call
grief craving the objects of the senses
is grief that grief is passed Beyond uh
when we no longer misperceive the
objects of our senses and then we are no
longer born in the Realms of pain and
thus do we pass beyond all grief thus do
we reach nirvana so he is very
interesting uh he wants to apply the
word grief to the objects of our senses
all right and and it's not wrong to say
uh one of them is ice cream all right
and then you know it's a very personal
subject for
me uh is it wrong to enjoy an ice cream
you see are
we are we not yogis if we enjoy an
occasional ice cream you know I'm
talking you're not overeating you're
fairly hungry you don't go to get an ice
cream every day it's like once a week uh
you did a couple of yoga classes it'll
balance out the calor you know and uh is
it all right to enjoy an ice cream you
see and and in in this tradition we say
yes it's fine you should enjoy your life
I mean your life is so short and violent
and and you know hard that if you get a
chance to have a you know vanilla ice
cream or stuff and then go for it you
know it's all right that's a pleasure
then then what would make it craving you
see what's the difference between
enjoying an ice cream and craving an ice
cream like I saw I always tell people I
have dinner with the Dal Lama you know
they said really I said yeah with
Harrison Ford too in in Washington DC
and then they said well how many other
people were there and I said
600 uh and then uh but I was close
enough to his table that I could watch
him eating dinner and I don't know
probably everybody in the room was
curious how the dama looks when he's
eating you know and you know does he
just pick out it like he you know and no
he goes for it you know he was like you
know he he was smiling he was taking
huge bites and then he was looking
around for
more and uh the the weird thing was he
seemed to be enjoying his dinner more
than anyone you know he was really uh
enjoying the food more than anyone so I
think a person who's uh made good
progress on the spiritual path they have
a an ability to enjoy things which is
even higher than other people you see
and yet they crave them less you see
they have less craving for them so they
crave them less and they enjoy them more
so but there's a deeper meaning of
craving I mean a basic craving a gross
craving obvious craving is where you
want it's a pringle
craving okay no I mean you open that
little thing you know you're smart you
still them in the little tubes but
usually we can get them in Big Tub and
then you just tear off the top and I
don't know why they put that tin foil
thing on it's like a spiritual obstacle
right no I mean it's like in your way
and you you should just take off the
plastic top and go right to the pingles
you know and then you pull off the top
pull off the
foil no there's this thing like I have
friends I have friends who can pick out
one and they they break it and they eat
it no I can't understand what they're
doing I'm trying to get them to
flow sometimes they get stuck they get
stuck in the opening and you have to
like
like that's that's a gross craving
right you don't need more you you're not
hungry you're you're not hungry at all
you know cuz you just had an ice cream
and you're mind mind gross craving is
when you keep eating when you there's no
possible reason to be eating except that
you feel nervous or something you know
you feel like just nervous and you want
to eat more so that's a gross craving
but that's not what he's talking about
that's not the craving for the six sense
of what he's talking about he says when
you misperceived them he says when you
don't understand them you know so what
does it mean to not understand an ice
cream cuz that's really the important
question it means if it it basically
means if you're wanting it uh would be
strong enough enough that you would hurt
someone else to get it then that's
craving okay if you're wanting it is
strong enough to like not share it with
someone else who wanted it then then
that would be craving why because you
couldn't do that if you understood where
the ice cream came from you see it's not
possible to not share ice cream if you
understand how to get
it got it okay it's not not possible uh
not to share ice cream if you understand
where the ice cream came from the ice
cream is a
projection of your mind from a seed that
was planted in your
subconscious uh from a time in the past
when you shared ice cream with
somebody is
that I don't think it's it doesn't
really matter let me put up here it
doesn't really matter whether it's up or
down is that okay
sure
uh if you understood that the Ice Cream
came from planting a seed in your mind
for ice cream from sharing the ice cream
you couldn't not share the ice cream got
it you would never not share ice cream
why you want you want it you want more
if you like ice cream you have to give
it away understand you have to you don't
have a choice if you are a real ice
cream Freak Like Me you must give it
away whenever you get a chance you have
to get away because that's how you get
War that's the only way you got the one
to give away anyway you understand so
that's understanding ice cream and
that's not craving okay it's not craving
it's understanding okay so what Lord
Buddha is saying is
that grief he's defining grief as
misunderstanding where things come
from okay
why in the case of ice cream
why why would be
grief it would be not having any and how
do you get
that you don't
share why don't you share cuz you have a
video what does a video tell you if I
don't eat it myself I won't get it okay
what does video tell you the only reason
I can get it is if I share understand
got it it's not wrong to want this
object of the senses it's wrong to Craig
them and craing means to misunderstand
them okay like that it's very
interesting it's not bad to eat ice
cream it doesn't hurt your
soul uh it doesn't ruin your chances for
Nirvana to misunderstand an ice cream it
hurts your chances for Nirvana whether
you eat it or not Swami G said that
today you know he was talking about
doing something or not doing something
it's the same thing if you misunderstand
it right so
[Music]
anyway that's grief to go beyond grief
for Lord Buddha and the way he defined
it in that Sutra was misunderstanding
where the stuff around you comes from is
grief because it is of the nature of
grief and it perpetuates grief okay got
it all
right okay I'll do one more thing and
then if you have questions I'll take
questions um so so I'd like you to
continue the meditation in the next 24
hours um what we were working on
yesterday was to admit to ourselves our
worst mental Affliction CLA okay I have
a weird experience I figured out
something uh lots of people come to me
with their problems and lots of people
come to me to confess things right then
they tell me I say okay just tell me
what happened and they'll tell me
something and I know know it's not the
worst thing I know it's the second worst
thing you know so I'll say you know like
they'll say I got to confess to you gu I
have jealousy you know I know that there
wor problem is anger and there's this
thing where we can't admit the number
one uh we tell everybody it's the number
two you see what I mean if if jealousy
is your second worst emotion and your
Lama asks you what is your worst emotion
you'll say jealousy cuz no one wants to
admit their first one you see we we we
don't want to admit to ourselves our
worst uh claa because it's so much a
part of our being you see and without it
we would be like someone remember when
you're a kid and you picked a pimple out
so the girls wouldn't think you were so
ugly and then it left a big
crater uh for like four days right uh
it's like that you know if you tore out
your you're number one mental fiction
you might let 80% of your mind might be
gone be all lonely in there you know
so so pick your worst one and be honest
it's refreshing it's so refreshing uh to
admit admitting your worst claa is half
of the war of defeating it you know half
you're halfway down if you can admit it
if you can admit your worst uh Habit to
yourself then you're half way through
overcoming it
uh then when I so that process is done
you have chosen with great honesty in
the last 24 hours the one uh negative
emotion that you have which is your most
serious form so we finished that
meditation now I want you to try a
different meditation
okay try to remember in the last few
days the times that you have done so
okay you still have a chance to have it
a few times before tomorrow morning when
you when you meditate right sometimes I
even have it during the
meditation uh that I start thinking
what's my worst emotion I think jealousy
and then I think about what and I think
about that other Buddhist teacher and
then then I start getting jealous of him
again during the
confession uh
so you still have time uh to have it
before your meditation session in the
morning right and then
um what I want you to explore really
from my heart what I want you to explore
is how it makes you feel just explore
how it makes you feel okay like I I've
been doing this practice you know and
then I was like examining my jealousy
and then I isolated a few jealousy
attacks that I had in the last few days
right and you know and normally I just
have them and I don't know notice that
I'm having them but I would I think what
I'm asking you is to try to notice that
you're having an attack of your worst
clure mental uh negative emotion right
but what I want you to explore is how it
makes your mind
feel when you're having it okay how it
makes your mind feel when you're having
it and I I wrote in the reading I had an
interesting experience the other day
somebody asked me to do a
video uh like a 3 minute video for some
charity
I did like Aid in one day for eight
right you were there eight day and a
half we did eight videos for different
charities so in the middle of talking
about one of the worthy
causes I thought of this person that I'm
jealous of and I actually stumbled when
I was speaking cuz I was thinking about
this person I'm jealous of and I forgot
what I was saying you know and then I
then I came back you know how you come
back and then I I just continued you
know please get M and then uh and
then now then I played it back to myself
a few times when I got home I had the
video and I played it back and I
observed myself having my favorite claa
and it was disgusting you know it was
really sad you know so here's this guy
he's say he's very reasonable saying you
know we have this great me these people
really need
your and you
know and I was watching myself it was
really sad uh cuz only I knew probably
people thought I dropped a pen or
something but I uh but I was just
thinking for a moment some I don't and
then I came back you know and so what I
want you to do
is I want you
to explore how it makes you feel when
you have it so you have two jobs try to
remember a time in the last few days
when you had your favorite claa but then
I want you to try to get in touch with
how it felt and how bad it felt okay and
how it chew you off balance
right the definition of it upsets the
Peace of Mind of a person while they are
entertaining it so I want you to try
just
to you know
remember one time in the last few days
when you had eaia and then try to
repaint the picture of how it felt in
your
mind how your mind felt during those few
moments and how about it because that is
grief got it that's the grief and it
feels really bad okay and I don't want
you to do anything about it I just want
you to feel it if you can't remember
having your favorite mental fliction you
can just bring one
up okay like think of someone you don't
like get upset and then observe how it
feels okay no you can do that I do that
sometimes just for
fun to observe how rather it is okay any
questions we have a few minutes
yeah
can wait was there you had one already
he didn't get one yet okay so I very
rarely
call anyone stupid but on
occasion I myself think that someone is
at least in
comp opening lines of the fourth chapter
of
the we just talked about which is the
chapter on where the world came from
Creator but in response to the question
of is there the Creator he opens his
chapter by saying L did not okay all the
planets of the universe came from the
karma of the people who live on
them raw karma is thought next line raw
karma is
thought and what we say and what we do
is only
secondary uh so
uh thinking strongly and clearly that
another person is stupid is a Karma and
it's very close to the core Karma it's
very close to the core in which the
karma is stored so it's much worse than
calling them stupid which is bad
news you know because I'm discreet but I
I think things a lot you know and yeah
it's raw Karma it's the heaviest kind of
Karma and it's it's immediately stored
and so we have to try
to work with our mind and not even
criticize people mentally yeah did you
have another question
okay one more then I think yeah if
anybody did you have one more what about
en I didn't catch it Envy Envy oh Envy
in a in an admirable way oh to admire
someone and wish we had their qualities
like that that's the definition of faith
in
Buddhism
sh
uh faith in Buddhism we call DEA and
it's calleda it has three kinds of sh
but the most famous one
is which means
um it means a clear faith and it means
but what it means in scripture is that
you admire the qualities of a person who
is especially a person who is more
spiritually advanced than you are and
then
you you aspire to the qualities that
they have and that's considered the
highest kind of Faith uh and the root of
all right effort uh because that kind of
Faith must preceive uh the effort
required to get those uh qualities so
they
call
say sh these are the four steps for
example for developing a meditation
practice if you have
trouble you people come to me and say
I've been trying for 10 years and and my
meditation practice sucks and I can't
get it it's just not happening you know
and then they would say in in the
Buddhist tradition they would say you
need
four pre practices
so that's the same thing means you have
to become convinced of all the cool
things that are going to happen to you
if you get if you learn to meditate
that's DEA you see you it you you
cultivate a jealousy of people who can
meditate which is a good jealousy I want
that then Duma means I want that H you
get a burning desire what did you call
that
Muk Muk I love that word I mean I don't
know anything about it but every time
says it I'm
like it's like a burning desire like I
want that thing okay that's number two
means you work hard because you want it
so bad you're willing to do the hard
work and you wouldn't want it if you
didn't feel jealous of someone who had
it already
Okay then shinjang means you get goddamn
good at it you just get really good
you know like I don't know at anything
like the way Swami G can teach scripture
that's a shinjang shinjang means you're
just really good at it because you
worked at it because you wanted it
because you were jealous in a good way
of people who already have it so that's
a virtue that's considered a
virtue to wish that they didn't have it
is a non virtual that's different okay
if it doesn't sink into that it's
okay let's stop there I'm going to do a
small
pair uh to give away the karma